So today's דף *daf* is פ"ב *Peh Bet*, 82. We pick up
on the משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* on the bottom of פ"א עמוד ב'
*Peh Aleph Amud Bet*.
And if you remember, the overarching discussion here is טומאה tumah *tumah*
of a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban pesach* that is טמא tamei
*tamei*, dealt with the case of ציבור *tzibur*, then we were dealing
with the case of an individual and how the ציץ *tzitz* operates
to make it acceptable, not to allow you to eat it, but
to make it acceptable if the meat or the blood becomes טמא
tamei *tamei* and even sometimes if the owners become טמא tamei *tamei*
in this category called טומאת התהום *tumat hatehom*. And now we are
going to deal with how you handle it when parts of it
do become טמא tamei *tamei*. But again to remind you that once
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban pesach* is brought and the דם
dam *dam* is נזרק *nizrak*, what happens afterwards does not affect whether
you were יוצא yotzei *yotze* the bringing of the פסח Pesach. *pesach*.
If you didn't eat it afterwards or if the meat became טמא
tamei *tamei* after, once it was brought and was fit to be
eaten, you were יוצא yotzei *yotze*. So the question about the מצווה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of eating is different, but it has to be brought
in a state in which it was fit to be eaten. Anyway,
now the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* deals with the question about what happens
if it did become טמא tamei, *tamei* after it was brought and
how you handle the meat. So let's take a look. נטמא כולו
או רובו *Nitmah kulo o rubo*, if the entirety of it became
טמא tamei *tamei*, before it was dismembered it came in contact with
something and then it would have happened, then it would have affected
the entirety of it, or the majority of it became טמא tamei.
*tamei*, the meat, again after it was brought, שורפין אותו לפני הבירה
sorfin oso lifnei habira מעצי המערכה *Sorfin oto lifnei habirah me'atzei hama'arachah*.
So what do you do with invalid קודשים *kodshim*? You burn it
in the presence of the בירה *Birah*, which literally means the castle,
here understood to be the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. It's
interesting that phrase,
and there could be even a little debate about exactly what that
phrase means, but we'll assume that's what it means. And you do
it from the wood that is used for the wood that is
designated for the fire on the altar, the מערכה ma'aracha, *ma'arachah* is
the wood pile on the altar. So you use sanctified wood that
normally would be used for the altar, you go into the presence
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash* and the גזבר *gizbar*,
the treasurer, whoever is in charge of the various stores, gives you
some of this wood and you can use it to burn your
פסח Pesach *pesach* that became טמא tamei *tamei*. Now, we will discuss
why it is. Now, the normal הלכה halakha *halakhah* is that קודשים
*kodshim* that become פסול possul *pasul* are burnt in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* quoted way back in the second פרק *perek* you might remember
and it's going to quote again briefly, בקודש באש תשרף bakodesh ba'esh
tisaref *bakodesh ba'esh tisaref*, כל שפסולה בקודש bakodesh. *kol shepasula bakodesh*. Is
number one, any sacrifice that became invalid, number one, you have to
be שורף *soref* it and number two, you שורף *soref* it בקודש
bakodesh *bakodesh*, you שורף *soref* it on holy ground, you שורף *soref*
it in the area, in the environs of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. The thing is, as we're about to see, that's
primarily things that are קודשי קודשים *kodshei kodashim*, things that when they
are valid have to be eaten and cannot leave the immediate area
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, cannot leave the עזרה
azarah *Azarah*. The פסח Pesach *pesach* can be eaten in all of
ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. So as we're going to see, there are scenarios
where you're allowed to burn it outside of the area of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? *Beit HaMikdash* because the meat itself when it
was כשר *kosher* was allowed to be eaten anywhere in ירושלים Yerushalayim
*Yerushalayim*. So let's keep on reading in the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. נטמא
מיעוטו *Nitma mi'uto*, let's say only a minority of it became טמא
tamei, *tamei* and the נותר nosar *notar*, it didn't become טמא tamei
*tamei*, you just didn't finish it and it was leftover meat. So
those are seen as cases that were less
grossly negligent when those things happened. So in those cases, שורפין אותו
בחצרותיהן או על גגותיהן *sorfin oto bechatzeroteihen o al gagoteihen*,
then you can burn it in your homes and in your yards,
presumably in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, which is where you were eating it.
You don't have to bring it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
*Beit HaMikdash*, but you still have to burn it, and מעצי עצמן
*me'atzei atzman*, and you have to use your own firewood.
So even if it
became טמא tamei
*tamei* in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*?
Yeah, because it doesn't matter where it became טמא tamei *tamei*. Now
the issues here being, there's two issues going on here which we'll
see also when we begin the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. One is where
you burn it and the other is what wood you use. Burning
it wherever you want is of course a lot easier on you,
you don't have to shlep it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
*Beit HaMikdash*. And we're actually going to see that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to say the reason when the entirety became טמא
tamei *tamei* you burn it in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit
HaMikdash* area is basically a fine, you were so negligent that you
let the whole thing become טמא tamei? *tamei*, we're going to have
to sort of inconvenience you and bring you to the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. And what's the purpose of that fine? There's,
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it's actually a little bit
of an element of a public
embarrassment that to dissuade people from this degree of negligence. Oh yeah,
look at that whole group burning their פסח Pesach *pesach* because right
there around the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* they were so
negligent. But as an interesting,
that's one issue about where you have to burn it. The other
issue is what wood you can use, because on the other hand
is the leniency to allow you to use the temple wood. Number
one, it's sanctified, so even if we wanted to let you use
it, how could we let you use it? So there רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* and תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* refer to another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that
says לב בית דין lev beis din מתנה עליהן *lev beit din
matneh aleihen*, which means that since anyway this is not sanctified the
way a קרבן korban, *korban*, it was only sanctified in terms of
an object owned by the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, the
wood,
then there can always be a
stipulation that the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* can choose to
use it if it sees fit in ways that are actually not
holy. actual usage, that they ultimately have control since it's more a
question of their ownership over it, that they can sort of stipulate
a certain amount of latitude of how they choose to use it
and when they choose to use it for non-הקדש hekdesh purposes, like
burning קרבנות korbanos which aren't direct הקדש hekdesh, purposes, burning פסול pasul
קרבנות, korbanos, then actually they could sort of almost, almost as it
were, remove the קדושה kedusha or stipulate that קדושה kedusha would not
be in effect under those circumstances. That's a whole separate סוגיא sugya
I don't want to get into, but I just want to make
note of it. But number one, besides the issue of how do
you deal with the fact that the wood is הקדש, hekdesh. is
that we're going easy on you, we're letting you use wood that
you don't have to pay for yourself, you don't have to provide
yourself. So it's an interesting balance of the question of the almost
being making it hard for you that you have to come to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to burn it, and going nice on
you providing the wood. And תוספות Tosfos, actually says that there is
that type of a balance. If you just look at the תוספות,
Tosfos
no, it's the owner of the פסח. Pesach נטמא רובה שורפין אותו
לפני הבירה, Nitma roba sorfin oso lifnei habira,
okay, so first he says, נראה דהיינו טעמא Nireh dehaynu ta'ama משום
דלב בית דין מתנה עליהם. mishum delev beis din masneh aleihem. So
לב בית דין מתנה עליהם lev beis din masneh aleihem is the
technical way in which it's not הקדש. hekdesh But now the practical
question of why did we let you use the wood? And he
says, לפי שהזקיקו לשורפו לפני הבירה כדי לביישו, lefi shehizkiku lesorfo lifnei
habira kedei levaysho, since we're already giving you such a hard time
and we're making you come to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. to
publicly shame you, to burn it in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash,
area,
therefore לא הכריחוהו להביא עצים משלו. lo hikrichu lehavi etzim mishelo. We're
not going to force you to provide your own firewood. The whole
procedure is embarrassing enough, we're going to in a way a little
bit go easy on you. So it's an interesting little balance, but
there are two separate considerations: whose wood and where. Let's just finish
the משנה. Mishnah הצייקנים Hatzeikanim
and the stingy people, שורפין אותו לפני הבירה בשביל ליהנות מעצי המערכה,
bishvil lehenos meatzei hama'aracha, they actually would go to the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash. burning area and they figured, you know what, we'll שלעפ
schlep out of our houses, at least we'll save ourselves the five
bucks on the firewood. So they would actually, even when they only
had a small amount and they weren't required, they would come to
this area of public burning in order, yeah, they wouldn't care about
the embarrassment, they wouldn't care about the שאנד, shand, they just didn't
want to use their own firewood and that's what they would do.
So the question is, תוספות Tosfos deals with this, it's very nice
that that's what they would like to do, but again the problem
is that why would we allow the wood to be used in
that capacity? So תוספות Tosfos says you have to say that for
those types of people, if they're willing to go and make the
שלעפ schlep and be embarrassed just in order to do it, clearly
if we would not let them use the wood and we would
insist that they provide their own firewood, they wouldn't have gone, they
wouldn't burn, they wouldn't burn the
the קרבן, korban, I mean what's left of it, the טמא tamei,
meat or the נותר nosar. meat. So we have to allow this
to happen because, I mean, if they're willing to go through all
those hoops clearly, you know, this is the way it's going to
get burnt when it needs to get burnt for these people. Michael's
been dying to ask a question, yes.
I'm just trying to understand this a little bit. Sometimes it's really
not your fault, like a שרץ sheretz just you know gets in
there and dies, what could you have done against it? So, you
know, to be embarrassed about that, that's one point.
Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara assumes the second part is, then if it really is
so gross like negligence, right, then why this is presumably paid for
by public funds, so why are public funds being used to cover
your negligence?
Alright, so the first answer is you're right, you can't automatically determine
every single case, but generally טומאה tumah happens if not due to
lack of vigilance, okay? If you're really treating הקדש hekdesh the way
you're supposed to, you should be hyper-vigilant about it. Is it possible
that things happen? Yes, but the combination that A, something happened and
B, it happened to the entire קרבן, korban I mean how long,
you know, that is unlikely unless there's a good degree of negligence.
Not a hundred percent but it's a reasonable assumption. As to the
issue of public funds, that's the issue I already discussed. I know,
it is funny, it's ironic, but that's תוספות's, Tosfos you know, תוספות's
Tosafos, answer is that once we're already imposing this real thing on
you, we're not going to make it like doubly embarrassing and I
have to like you know provide your own you know provide the
materials for your own execution. Like that far we're not going to
go. If it's, I can just
have it burned anyway, I can just burn it in my backyard
and use my own wood.
No, we won't let you.
Why? Why would you want to?
Yes, yes, exactly. Let's just read the first line in the גמרא
Gemara to put an end to this. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why
do we make you do it if it's the whole פסח Pesach
in the front of the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash. אמר רב יוסף
אמר רב חנינא Amar Rav Yosef Amar Rav Chanina כדי לביישן kedei
le-vayshan in order to embarrass them. Okay, not like we get pleasure
out of embarrassing them, but hopefully it makes people everybody else be
that much more careful. Do, you had a question. I have two
technical, I'm sorry, you had to have a second, okay, the
the phrase לב בית דין Beis Din refers to the court of
כהנים? Kohanim?
No, that's another interesting point which is is that, you know, I
mean historically we sort of know that, you know, the period, well,
yes, I mean there was obviously a סנהדרין Sanhedrin operating but we
also know that the more seat of religious and political authority for
a long time was in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. and the
כהנים Kohanim and sort of the rabbis rose more to prominence as
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was sort of
declining. But in the eyes of חז"ל, Chazal, ultimately
everything that goes on in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is overseen
by the rabbis and therefore even issues about הקדש hekdesh and how
it's used and all those things is ultimately determined by a בית
דין Beis Din by some central בית דין Beis Din yeah could
be the you know could be the idea of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
in the לשכת הגזית Lishkas HaGazit presence of the בית דין Beis
Din exactly which בית דין Beis Din or is it like a
hypothetical בית דין you know what חז"ל Chazal would have wanted but
yes there is this idea that it's a rabbinic authority ultimately overseeing
the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and that phrase מתנה עליהם matneh aleihem עליהם
aleihem is the
עצים eitzim yes
correct yes טוב tov number two if it becomes טמא tamei before
it's eaten yes do these people have to bring another no
so that's what I was saying in the beginning is again to
remember that there's one question of was I מקריב makriv the קרבן
korban and that's the issue of חיוב כרת chiyuv kares פסח שני
Pesach Sheini so if I was מקריב makriv the קרבן korban and
it was fit to be eaten when the blood was thrown I
was יוצא yotzei my חיוב קרבן chiyuv korban and I don't bring
a פסח שני Pesach Sheini if now the meat becomes טמא tamei.
or it all burns or I fall asleep and I don't eat
it or whatever I didn't do my מצווה of eating פסח Pesach
meat that night
do you bring another פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon in
order to eat פסח Pesach meat no if you were already נמנה
nimneh on a פסח Pesach could you be נמנה nimneh on another
פסח pesach. if you had time
interesting possibly that's an interesting question I'm
talking about the economics of it because it could be economical just
having to replace a קרבן korban the meat is more expensive than
the wood
to burn it right clearly you wouldn't only be obligated but that's
an interesting question we definitely are going to get like for example
when we get to the discussion of women a category of רשות
reshus where you don't have to be part of a קרבן פסח
korban Pesach. I mean that's a debate whether women are רשות reshus
or חובה chovah but you're able to be so you certainly יוצא
yotzei here can I bring another קרבן korban after I was יוצא
yotzei in order to be able to eat the meat of the
פסח pesach let me see if I can find something I don't
know can
you join another חבורה chaburah
right well that's the thing I mean a way to do it
would be to part of another חבורה chaburah but if you were
already
right exactly exactly I mean you'd have to yes well that's the
question that's an interesting question whether you could if you brought it
but weren't able to eat the meat okay I mean normally the
הלכה halacha is you can't be part of two חבורות chaburos but
the question is are you part of two חבורות chaburos if you
were part of a חבורה chaburah for the הקרבה hakravah but not
for the אכילה achilah so it's an interesting question yeah
related what if the שוחט shochet screws up the שחיטה shechitah making
it a נבילה neveilah which also makes it טמא tamei then you
would never יוצא forget נבילה neveilah then you weren't יוצא then the
קרבן korban is פסול pasul then of course you have to bring
another קרבן korban if you have time and not you bring a
פסח שני Pesach Sheini all right let's take a look as the
גמרא Gemara continues איתמר מיעוטו itmar mi'uto
if it's only a minority of it רמיהו ramihu says the גמרא
Gemara after a bit וכן מי שיצא מירושלים ונזכר שיש בידו בשר
קדש v'chen mi sheyatzah mi'Yerushalayim venizkar sheyeish biyado basar kodesh we learned
this much earlier you were walking out of ירושלים Yerushalayim and you
realized that you had some שלמים shelamim meat on you now because
it's שלמים shelamim meat you which could be eaten in all of
ירושלים Yerushalayim again if it was קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim you would
have no choice you would have to burn it in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash area but because it is שלמים shelamim meat in
theory you could have you know more there's greater latitude where you
could burn it so you were walking out and you realized that
you had some שלמים shelamim meat left in your knapsack so אם
עבר צופים im avar Tzofim if you passed צופים Tzofim which could
be הר צופים Har Tzofim or could be basically the places you
know the way רש"י Rashi, understands it is the area from which
you could see ירושלים Yerushalayim you're now so far outside of ירושלים
Yerushalayim that you no longer have a view of ירושלים Yerushalayim from
where you are so you're no longer considered to be in the
environs of ירושלים Yerushalayim in that case שורפו במקומו sorefo bimkomo we
allow you to burn it where you are we don't ask you
to schlep all the way back ואם לאו v'im lav and if
not חוזר ושורפו לפני הבירה מעצי המערכה chozer vesorefo lifnei habirah me'eitzim
hama'arachah
same story you have to schlep back because you're still close enough
to ירושלים Yerushalayim but you get to use the firewood of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash so there's two issues going on here one
is under what circumstances do we ask you to schlep back but
the other thing is when you actually are going back then you
can use the firewood of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. and the
גמרא's Gemara question is
basically how come this guy when he does schlep back he's allowed
to use the firewood why is that different than the case in
the משנה Mishnah where I realize I have a little meat of
the קרבן פסח korban pesach, left over or a little meat that
became טמא tamei and I'm in ירושלים Yerushalayim, why shouldn't I be
allowed to go to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and use their
firewood so it's not a question of why there could be you
could have asked two questions why aren't I obligated right here it
sounds like I'm obligated to go back and our משנה Mishnah says
that you're allowed to do it at home again there's two issues
location and wood okay but the issue the גמרא Gemara. is focusing
on right now is not why in the משנה Mishnah am I
allowed to stay home but why in the משנה mishna. am I
not able to go to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. and to
use that wood
yeah the משנה mishna. doesn't give you that option yes we'll see
what the גמרא Gemara
says what's someone doing taking קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim out of ירושלים
Yerushalayim.
it's קדשים קלים kodashim kalim I said שלמים shelamim meat okay so
you're eating it in ירושלים Yerushalayim. and then you packed up your
meat you know whatever and you forgot and you started going home
okay אמר רב חנא amar Rav Chana אמר רב חמא בר עוקבא
*Amar Rav Chama bar Ukva*, so again there's two questions: location and
wood. We're focusing on the wood aspect. Why here do you use
the wood of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* and you're
allowed to go to that area and our משנה mishna. *Mishnah* presumably
you only do it at home? So, לא קשיא *lo kashya*, כאן
באכסנאי כאן בבעל הבית *kan be'achsanya kan be'ba'al habayis*.
It depends: are you a homeowner or are you a visitor? If
you are in the משנה *Mishnah*, why are you leaving ירושלים *Yerushalayim*?
In the ברייתא Braita *Braisa*, why are you leaving ירושלים *Yerushalayim*
because you don't live there? So in that case, if you don't
live there, we're not going to expect you necessarily to have your
own wood. So in that case, even if you weren't on the
process of leaving ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, if you were in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* because
it was פסח *Pesach* but you didn't live there, you'd be allowed
to go to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* area and
use their wood. The משנה *Mishnah* that says
you do it at home,
yes let's we'll worry about it Michael, I'm aware of the problem.
Let the case of the משנה *Mishnah* which says that you do
it at home, excuse me, which says that you do it in
your homes, that's people that live in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, they are not
given the option of or not allowed, right, not given the option
of going to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, they must
stay at home and use their own wood. רב פפא אמר *Rav
Pappa amar*, הא והא באכסנאי *ha v'ha be'achsanya*. You know, you can
even make a distinction between two types of visitors. כאן שהחזיק בדרך
כאן שלא החזיק בדרך *kan shehecheshik baderech kan shelo hecheshik baderech*.
If you're a visitor there because you're coming to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* for
פסח *Pesach* but you haven't started leaving yet, you're still at whatever
hotel or whatever person is putting you up. So for the time
being you're now a temporary resident, you're not in the process of
leaving. In that case, the same way every morning you wake up
and you have to worry about breakfast, we can tell you you
have to worry about getting the wood and therefore you'll have to
provide your own wood and do it at home. In the ברייתא
braita *Braisa*, you were already in the process of leaving. In that
case, to now make you worry about going to a store again
and finding wood and this and that, in that case your body
and mind is already outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so we allow you
to just go to the public burning of it and not worry
about your own wood.
Can we do that to the guy who's already started leaving?
Exactly, that's the ברייתא *Braisa* where he uses the wood of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*. So then we go to the
next גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. All right. Yes. Let's just finish. רב זביד
אמר לעולם כדאמרן מעיקרא *Rav Zvid amar l'olam k'da'amran me'ikara*, it's like
we said originally that it's not about in the process of leaving
or not. כאן באכסנאי כאן בבעל הבית *kan be'achsanya kan be'ba'al habayis*,
ואף על גב דהחזיק בדרך *ve'af al gav de'hecheshik baderech*,
but he's
repeating the first position, just says he's clarifying the first position anyway.
It's all about being a guest or a homeowner. It doesn't matter
if you're in the process of leaving or you're not in the
process of leaving. Anybody who's a guest is entitled to use the
wood of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. Why? אכסנאי כיון
דלית ליה *achsanya keivan delais lei*,
since a guest doesn't have his own, you know, his own
property here in the city, so עשו כמי שאין לו *asu kemi
she'ein lo*, they treated him even if you weren't in the process
of leaving, they treated him like the stingy people. They put him
in the category of people that don't have the option or a
reasonable option of using their own wood psychologically or practically and therefore
דלאו תיקנו ליה לשרפו לפני הבירה בשביל הנאה של המארח *delav tiknu
lei lesorfu lifnei habirah bishvil hana'ah shel ham'are'ach*.
So again in this whole discussion, it seems that the only concern
is: do you have to use your own wood or could use
the wood of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. It does
not discuss the issue about demanding where you go in order to
take care of it, right? You could have asked the other question.
You could have said that in the משנה *Mishnah* says you're allowed
to burn it in your home and in the ברייתא *Braisa* it
says that you have to go ahead and schlep back to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, right? So what about that difference?
So רש"י Rashi. *Rashi* a little bit addresses that problem. רש"י *Rashi*
says at the end of רב זביד *Rav Zvid*, let's see, about
three lines down in the narrow lines, he says והחזיק בדרך כדקתני
מתניתין *ve'hecheshik baderech kedekatani masnisin*. According to רב זביד'ס *Rav Zvid's* idea
that it's all about being a guest and using the wood because
you're a guest and it doesn't matter whether you started your journey
or not, why did the ברייתא *Braisa* speak about being on your
journey? לאשמועינן חזרה נקט לה *le'ashme'inan chazara nakat lah* to tell you
that even though you started your journey you have to come back,
ולא משום עצים דהוא הדין ללא החזיק *velo mishum etzim de'hu hadin
lelo hecheshik*. Okay,
so רש"י *Rashi* a little bit emphasizes the idea that the ברייתא
*Braisa* is coming to underscore that even if you're on your journey,
we're going to schlep you back and demand that you come back.
But again what רש"י *Rashi* is not being clear about is, okay
I'm a guest, you're telling me I don't care that you're on
your journey, if you haven't left, if you're still in sight of
ירושלים *Yerushalayim* you have to turn around, fine I get all of
that. And I get that you're being nice to me and telling
me that as a guest I'm allowed to use the wood of
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, but why are you forcing me to
go, you know, back to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, back to
the הר הבית Har HaBayis. *Har Habayis*? Why can't I just burn
it anywhere? So that's not clear. I mean, again, there's an issue
of being nice to me by letting me use the wood, but
there's an issue of putting a demand on me that I actually
go back to the הר הבית Har HaBayis? *Har Habayis*. So I
think you could suggest one of two answers. One is that the
משנה *Mishnah*, the ברייתא *Braisa* that tells me I have to go
back to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is telling me that A,
I have to go back, number one, to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Number two
is if I want to use the wood of the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash*, I can do that by going back to the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. If I wanted to, I could just go to
ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and use my own wood, so it's really not demanding
that I go back to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, but it's
giving me that option if I want to use that wood. Another
possibility is just to say, look, maybe the אכסנאי *achsanya* can work.
against me as well. If I live at home and I'm at
home, so then they'll tell me, you know what, you don't have
to שלעפ shlep, out of your house, you're entitled to stay at
home and burn it at home. Okay, if I'm a guest and
I'm traveling and I was already leaving, once I was already leaving,
once I've got to come back anyway, why should I be entitled
to go to somebody's house and burn it? Once I've already left
the house and I'm no longer rooted in any location, then once
I'm coming back, we're going to demand that I come back and
do it in front of the בית המקדש. So it's not exactly
clear. The גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss it. Again, what's confusing here is
two different considerations. One is a חומרא chumra and one is a
קולא. kula. When you go to the בית המקדש, the חומרא chumra
is we demand that you שלעפ, it could be embarrassing, you're doing
it in public, but the קולא kula is you get to use
the wood of the בית המקדש. Okay, so in the משנה we
had the case where we were trying to make things bad for
you because you let the whole thing become טמא, tamei, but we
go easy on you with the wood. In the ברייתא it's a
little bit the reverse. You're a guest, you're a traveler, you're leaving,
we want to go easy on you and let you use the
wood, but it's not so clear why we demand that you go
to the בית המקדש. Why don't we at least give you the
option that if you wanted to, you could do it somewhere else
and use your own wood? And maybe the answer is אי נמי,
ei nami, maybe I do have that option, but that's not being
explained.
Would you say that this category צקנים tzikanim is an halakhic category
that takes one's psychological or anthropological condition into account? Totally, because it
doesn't talk about עניים, aniyim, it talks about צקנים. tzikanim.
So who gets to identify who's in that category? I guess self-selecting.
Anybody who's willing to go to the public space and go through
this embarrassment or whatever, you're in that category. Yeah, mostly I'm actually
a resident but I'm packing up on a vacation, you know?
Yeah, so apparently, right, that doesn't seem to, yeah, I don't know.
All right, so let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara
continues. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, because now we're going to get a
little
bit of a flip case about the focus of the location issue.
Let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, באו לשרפה בחצרותיהן מעצי
המערכה. ba'u lisreifa bechatzeroteihen meetzei hama'aracha. Somebody says, you know what I'd
like to do? I'd like to burn it privately in my house,
but I'd like to use the wood of the בית המקדש. Okay,
אין שומעין להם, ein shomin lahem, you don't let them. Now maybe
even if it's the צקנים tzikanim where you're anyway going to make
it easier for me because or else if you don't let me
use your wood I won't burn it, we still won't let me
do it privately. לפני הבירה מעצי עצמן. lifnei habira meetzei atzman. Let's
say I want to do it in the public space but I
want to use my own wood for some bizarre reason, אין שומעין
להם, ein shomin lahem, you don't allow it. So now the גמרא
Gemara is going to unpack. בשלמא מעצי המערכה בחצרותיהן, bishlama meetzei hama'aracha
bechatzeroteihen, I get why you don't let me do it in my
own yard with the wood of the בית המקדש even if it
was like the case of צקנים tzikanim where you're not trying to
embarrass me, אין שומעין להם, ein shomin lahem, you don't listen. דילמא
פייש מינייהו, dilma payish mineihu, because maybe some of the wood will
be left over, ואיידי דהקדש הוא, ve'aidei dehekdesh hu, and since it
would have been הקדש hekdesh. otherwise if I wasn't using it, anything
left over remains הקדש. Hekdesh And if I'm doing it in my
yard and I have leftover wood, I'll keep it for myself, ואתו
בה לידי תקלה, ve'atu bah lidei takala, you'll come to stumble, meaning
I'll come to use the leftover wood for other purposes. אלא לפני
הבירה מעצי עצמן מאי טעמא לא, ela lifnei habira meetzei atzman mai
ta'ama lo, but why can't I go ahead and do it in
the public space in front of the בית המקדש and use my
own wood? Right? Why not? If I want to save the בית
המקדש the money? רב יוסף אמר כדי שלא לבייש את מי שאין
לו, Rav Yosef amar kedei shelo levayesh et mi she'ein lo, not
to embarrass, once you start saying, oh well, you know, if you're
really a little bit of a more generous person you'd be bringing
your own wood, then all of a sudden, you know, everybody who
doesn't bring their own wood and uses the public wood is being
embarrassed. That is a good point, whole point is to embarrass but
again, but if maybe we're talking about the צקנים, tzikanim, you know,
maybe we're talking about the guest. We're not necessarily trying to embarrass
everybody or we're not trying to embarrass them more than is appropriate
to embarrass them. But it's a good point, within that context of
doing this a little bit to embarrass, we're still being sensitive to
issues of dignity. So he says, you don't want it to be
that, by the way, becomes an issue in a number of places,
the הלכה halacha for example, about like if you get called up
for an עליה. aliyah. In the ספרדי Sephardi מנין, minyan, if you
know how to read and you get called up for an עליה,
aliyah, you're expected to read. But you know, in אשכנזי Ashkenazi מנינים,
minyanim, we don't do that. Often because the guy, you know, might
have been being paid, the בעל קורא, ba'al koreh, to prepare it
and anyway I spent the whole week preparing, you're going to come
up and you're going to take my עליה. aliyah. But the other
reason that's given is שלא לבייש את מי שאין לו. shelo levayesh
et mi she'ein lo. If all of a sudden you're allowed to
read when you get called up for an עליה, aliyah, then anybody
who doesn't read is embarrassed because you're basically making a statement that
they don't know the עליה. aliyah. So the better point so the
policy is nobody gets to read in order that it doesn't make
a difference between who knows and who doesn't know. They actually some
have said that that's where the institution came for the מסדר קידושין
mesader kiddushin to make the ברכת אירוסין, birkat eirusin, that it used
to be made by the חתן, chatan, but that not all of
the חתנים chatanim knew the ברכה. bracha. So the מסדר mesader would
make it. But then oh some are going to make it and
some aren't, so that makes it clear who's illiterate and who doesn't
know the ברכה, bracha, so nobody gets to make it. That's a
crazy prophet! Yeah, everyone's a prophet! What can I tell you? This
was actually before this was before printed סידורים. siddurim. So this is
the idea, we don't make distinctions. You want to be a צדיק
tzaddik and bring your own wood, I'm sorry, that's going to wind
up embarrassing other people. כדי שלא לבייש את מי שאין לו. kedei
shelo levayesh et mi she'ein lo. רב פפא אמר מפני החשד. Rav
Papa amar mipnei hachashad. No, because of suspicion. What's the suspicion? You're
going to bring your own firewood, you'll burn some, and then you'll
take the remainder of the firewood home. So people will think that
that's הקדש Hekdesh. firewood you're taking home. מה בינייהו? Ma beinaihu? What's
the difference between them? איכא בינייהו דאייתי קנה וחריותא. Ika beinaihu d'aiti
kaneh v'charyusa. You're bringing reeds and like palm branches, things that would
never be used for the wood on the altar, would clearly not
be הקדש. בלאו הכי Belav hachi for the מערכה, those things are
so like they burn so quickly, you know, it's like burning paper.
So nobody's going to use it as real firewood on the altar.
So there's no חשד, chashad, nobody suspects that it's anything other than
your own. But there is a problem about embarrassing others. תנן התם.
Tenan hasam. Now we have a similar debate of רבא Rava and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef in another context. ראש המעמד היה מעמיד. Rosh
hama'amad hayah ma'amid. This was in תמיד, Tamid, for those who were
with us last year and finished up ש"ס, Shas, you might remember
this. So the head of the group of the כהנים Kohanim for
that day, היה מעמיד את הטמאים בשער המזרח. hayah ma'amid es hatme'im
besha'ar hamizrach. I'm not exactly anyway the person who was like the
office manager, that's the wrong way anyway the guy who was on
the ground, the floor foreman, okay, in the בית המקדש for that
day, היה מעמיד את הטמאים בשער המזרח. hayah ma'amid es hatme'im besha'ar
hamizrach, You take all the טמאי כהנים tamei Kohanim for that day
and make them stand by the eastern gate entering into the עזרת
נשים. Ezras Nashim. So in the beginning of the day. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef כדי לביישן, k'dei l'vayeshan,
to publicly embarrass them. You allowed yourselves to become טמא and, you
know, we gotta shame you. And again, hopefully as a way of
making everybody careful, not that we get pleasure in shaming you, but
makes everybody more careful. So where he said in the case of
the firewood it was to protect them from embarrassment, in this case
he's saying it's in order to embarrass them. But the point is
he's always focusing on that concern of embarrassment. רבא אמר Rava amar
מפני החשד. mipnei hachashad. רבא Rava says the same thing, a suspicion.
What's suspicion here? That people will see, you know, will come to
the בית המקדש and say, "Hey, where's חיים? Chaim? Why's חיים Chaim
not working today? It's his day in the בית המקדש. Hey, he's
probably, you know, goofing off, or he's probably decided he has to
go do his, you know, go to his normal job, his, you
know, computers or he's a doctor and he couldn't take the time
to come to the בית המקדש today." So people are going to
suspect you if they don't see you in the בית המקדש. So
therefore, anybody walking into the בית המקדש sees that you're being, you're
in that, you know, that you're standing over there in the טמאים
tme'im location. So that's a little funny. So you don't suspect that
I'm just סתם stam goofing off, you understand the reason I'm not
working in the בית המקדש today is because I'm טמא. So מאי
בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what's the difference between them? איכא בינייהו מפנקי. Ika
beinaihu mefanki. Let's say it's people that are basically unemployed, you know,
it means like literally like what's a good word for מפנקי? mefanki?
Spoiled or whatever, yeah, meaning people that are idle, people that don't
have a job. So if I don't have a job, nobody is
going to suspect me, apparently you're not going to suspect I'm going
to the movies to get out of the בית המקדש. I mean
it was an honorable thing to do the בית המקדש. So if
you're going to suspect me, you're going to suspect me that I'm
not there because I'm earning a living. But if I don't need
to earn a living, if I'm independently wealthy, then nobody will suspect
me why I'm not there. אינמי דקדיש שישורא Inami d'kadish shishura or
another thing, I have a job that is extremely low paying, that
basically I weave like, you know, palm branches or something. So that
type of a thing, it's so low paying, I'm not leaving the
בית המקדש to get a few pennies today. So nobody would have
suspected me for leaving the work for my עבודה, avodah, so you
don't need to do it for that purpose. But according to רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, you'd still do it כדי לביישן. k'dei l'vayeshan. I
should point out by the way in terms of what טומאה tuma
we're talking about, I don't know, I keep on going back to
this, maybe it's a little pet peeve of mine, but if you
look at this תוספות, Tosafos היה מעמיד את הטמאים hayah ma'amid es
hatme'im בשער המזרח, besha'ar hamizrach. תוספות Tosfos says like this, אפילו בטומאת
קרי מיירי, afilu b'tumas keri mairi, even somebody that was טמא because
he had a seminal emission the night before and even if he
had gone to the מקווה mikvah that morning. ונראה לי דהאי שער
מזרח היינו שער עזרת נשים. V'nira li de'hai sha'ar mizrach haynu sha'ar
Ezras Nashim. דאף על גב דבפרק קמא דיבמות ובכמה דוכתי דטבול יום
אינו נכנס למחנה לוייה. D'af al gav d'veperek kama d'Yevamos u'vchama duchti
d'tevul yom eino nichnas l'machaneh Leviyah. So even if I'd gone to
the מקווה mikvah this morning, I'm still a טבול יום, tevul yom,
it's not right, and therefore I should have to get out of
all of הר הבית. Har HaBayis, Why do they put me by
the eastern gate which is before the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim but
it's still on הר הבית? Har HaBayis לא בכל מחנה לוייה אלא
מעזרת נשים ולפנים. Lo b'chol machaneh Leviyah ela m'Ezras Nashim u'lifnim. Somebody
who's a טבול יום tevul yom is only אסור asur for like
קרי keri is only אסור asur from, you know, where עזרת נשים
Ezras Nashim begins. Anyway, again I raise this because of this whole
issue about people that go on the Temple Mount. So even if
a man actually had sex the night before or he was a
בעל קרי ba'al keri and even if he had gone to the
מקווה mikvah that morning, he's not allowed into the עזרת נשים Ezras
Nashim area. Even when they go on הר הבית, Har HaBayis. not
just into the
actual area of the עזרה azarah.
but even the area of the עזרת נשים.
Ezras Nashim. So and according to some he wouldn't be allowed on
הר הבית altogether.
So again, something that I don't think people pay enough attention to.
Alright, moving on, next משנה. Maybe I'm just jealous because I've never
gone up to הר הבית. Alright, so let's take a look at
the next משנה. הפסח שיצא או שנטמא ישרף מיד. HaPesach she'yatza o
shenitma yisaref miyad. Now before we talked about where it gets burned,
now we talk about the fact that it does get burned. So
if it went out of the... meaning it went out of ירושלים,
or it became טמא, you burn it immediately. נטמאו הבעלים או שמתו.
Nitmu ha-ba'alim o she-meisu. Now if the problem is not intrinsic to
the meat, but external:
the owners became טמא and therefore not able to eat it because
you can't have somebody who
isn't an owner eat it.
So it's nobody's able to eat it. Or the owners died, similar
scenario in terms of
no owners to eat it. תעובר צורתו וישרף בששה עשר. Tu'ubar tzurato
veyisaref beshishas'ar. You have to let it, literally it means its appearance
degrades, but basically that's a phrase to mean you let it sleep
over the night and therefore it's פסול בלינה pasul belina because it's
נותר. nosar, It's now the next morning, the morning of the 15th,
but you can't burn it on the 15th because you don't burn
פסול קדשים pasul kodshim on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So therefore you
actually have to wait to burn it till the 16th. רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא אומר Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer אף זה ישרף מיד.
af zeh yisaref miyad. Even when there are no owners you burn
it immediately on the 14th. Nobody's burning anything on the 15th which
is יום טוב. Yom Tov. But if the owners died or became
טמא on the 14th you would burn it immediately. לפי שאין לו
אוכלים. Lefi she'ein lo ochlim. Because if there's nobody to eat it,
that's like an intrinsic invalidity in the פסח and you would burn
it. So the basic principle is when it's a פסול הגוף, psul
haguf, what's called an intrinsic invalidity, you burn it immediately. So if
it's the 14th you burn on the 14th. If it's something external
to it that makes it not usable, you wait for it to
become נותר, nosar. which means you wait till the 15th, but because
you can't burn קדשים kodshim that are פסול psul on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, you burn it on the 16th. And then the question
becomes what's considered internal פסול psul, and what's considered an external one.
What's the case of שיצא? sheyatza? What's that? It means that it
went out of its acceptable boundaries, which means out of ירושלים. If
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodshim, it would mean it left the עזרה. azarah
By the פסח it means it went out of ירושלים. And in
the case of the בעל קרי, ba'al keri, does any כהן kohen
that had sex with his wife the night before stand by the
Eastern Gate the next... Well, if you're on, if you're working that
week and anyway they even had a... that the whole week of
כהנים kohanim were divided by days. So okay, for one night before,
you know, you don't, you know, so in order that you're fit
the next morning. All right. But the bigger question like I told
you in the past was if you פוסק pasken that a בעל
קרי ba'al keri is אסור assur in מחנה לויה, machaneh Leviyah, then
when they were in the מדבר, midbar, anybody that any לוי Levi
that had sex with his wife would have to get up in
the middle of the night and leave, right? How was he even
allowed to have sex with his wife and to become a בעל
קרי ba'al keri while he was in מחנה לויה? machaneh Leviyah? I
don't understand. All right, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
בשלמא טמא כתיב. Bishlama tamei ksiv. I get when it's טמא that
you have to burn it. The פסוק pasuk says: והבשר אשר יגע
בכל טמא לא יאכל באש ישרף. Vehabasar asher yiga bechol tamei lo
yei'achel ba'esh yisaref. It's a פסוק pasuk that if it becomes טמא
don't eat it, burn it. אלא יצא מנלן? Ella yatza minalan? Where
is this idea that if it goes out of its boundaries it
has to be burned? So the גמרא Gemara says דכתיב diksiv the
פסוק pasuk says by Moshe and Aharon, right, that Aharon burned the
חטאת chatas and Moshe wanted to understand what it was all about
on the מלואים. miluim. It says: הן לא הובא את דמו אל
הקדש פנימה. Hen lo huva et damo el hakodesh penimah. The blood
wasn't brought inside, right, because a קרבן korban, that is supposed to
have the blood sprinkled on the outside, a חטאת, chatas, it has
the blood brought into the היכל, heichal, the Torah says that you
have to burn it. So Moshe said, but this did not have
the blood brought to the inside פנימה, penimah, inside. So אמר ליה
משה לאהרן. amar lei Moshe le'Aharon. Moshe said to Aharon: מדוע לא
אכלתם את החטאת? Madua lo achaltem et hachatas? Why did you not
eat this חטאת? chatas? שמא נכנס דמה לפני ולפנים? Shema nichnas damah
lifnai velifnim? Is it possible you brought the blood into the innermost
sanctum into the היכל heichal and therefore that invalidated it and therefore
then you would burn a חטאת chatas if you did that? אמר
לו לאו. Amar lo lav. No, that's not what happened. אמר לו.
Amar lo. So Moshe said: שמא חוץ למחיצתה יצאה? Shema chutz limchitzasah
yatzah? Maybe the meat went outside of its boundaries, it left the
עזרה azarah and that's why you burned it? אמר לו לאו. Amar
lo lav. No, בקדש היתה. bakodesh hayasah. It was in the קודש.
kodesh. אמר לו. Amar lo. אי בקדש היתה, Ei bakodesh hayasah, if
it was in the קודש, kodesh, it didn't go too much in
and it didn't go out, והן לא הובא את דמה אל הקדש
פנימה, vehen lo huva et damah el hakodesh penimah, and it didn't
go too much inside פנימה, penimah, inside, it didn't go into a
zone it wasn't allowed, מדוע לא אכלתם אותה? madua lo achaltem osah?
Why did you not eat it? Now we don't get the answer.
But what's וייכש? vayechesh? I know, well what does that answer mean?
That's debate. But okay, but anyway, the point is is that the
way חז"ל Chazal are reading it is הן לא הובא את דמה
אל הקדש. hen lo huva et damah el hakodesh. You didn't bring
the blood inside. And then this is the way Rashi understands how
the גמרא Gemara is reading the next part into it: פנימה. penimah.
It remained on the inside. So it didn't go too much in
and it didn't go out either. It was פנימה. penimah. It's sort
of read as, right, it stayed in the בית המקדש grounds, in
the משכן Mishkan grounds. So אכול תאכלו אותה בקדש. achol tochlu osah
bakodesh. You should have eaten it בקדש. bakodesh. Tosafot says the דרש
drash is on the word בקדש. bakodesh. אכול תאכלו אותה בקדש. achol
tochlu osah bakodesh. Since it remained בקדש bakodesh in the עזרה azarah,
grounds you should have eaten it. But either from the word פנימה
penimah or בקדש bakodesh we're understanding that part of the point was
it didn't go too much in but it also didn't go out.
And if it would have gone out, it would have made sense
that you would have burned it. Ah, so the שקלא וטריא shakla
vetarya is emphasizing Moshe's question. Right, we're inferring... I don't care why
he didn't eat it. Not for now. But we're inferring under what
circumstances it would have been justified to burn it. מכלל דאם נפקא,
Miklal de'im nafkuh, you see that had it gone out, if it
wasn't פנימה, penimah, wasn't בקדש, bakodesh, אי נמי עייל דמה לפנים, i
nami ayyel damah lifnim, or it had gone into the... So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says fine. בשלמא נטמא *Bishlama nitmah* good. So
now we have our two sources of נטמא *nitmah* and יצא *yatzah*.
Now I get נטמא *nitmah*, גלי רחמנא *gali rachmana* by קדשים kodshim?
קלים *kadashim kalim*, the Torah talks about a case of קדשים קלים
*kadashim kalim*, כל שכן *kol she-ken* and some say והוא הדין *ve-hu
ha-din* the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim, *kodshei kodashim*, I mean it applies
to all קרבנות korbanos *korbanos*, it doesn't distinguish, anything that becomes טמא
*tamei* you burn it. אלא יוצא *Ela yotzei*, the idea of going
out of its zone, right, which was by the חטאת chatas. *chatas*,
so אשכחן *ashkachan* in the case by Moshe and Aharon, אשכחן קדשי
קדשים kadshei kodshim *ashkachan kodshei kodashim*, that's קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim*, קדשים
קלים מנלן *kadashim kalim minalan*? How do I know by קדשים קלים
*kadashim kalim*? And not only because קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* are more
lenient so therefore maybe you know we shouldn't be as strict. But
it's also because what defines יוצא *yotzei* is different. קדשים קלים *kadashim
kalim* are allowed to be eaten in all of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So
the idea that there's a zone that you can't leave which it's
really sort of has drastic implications to leave might only apply when
that zone is the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. As soon as you're
allowed to eat it in all of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, who knows whether
crossing that line is so severe that it would invalidate the meat
and demand that it be burned. Okay, number two, that's question number
one. And number two, הא דתניא detanya, *ha de-tanya*, we have another
ברייתא *braisa*, לן דמא *lan dama*, if its blood slept, meaning the
blood went, you know, it became nightfall and you didn't do the
זריקת הדם zerikat hadam. *zrikas ha-dam*. The זריקת הדם zerikat hadam *zrikas
ha-dam* has to be done while it's day. Or נשפך דמא nishpach
dama *nishpach dama*, the blood got spilled. יצא דמא חוץ לקלעים *Yatzah
dama chutz le-klaim*, or the blood was taken out of the literally
curtains, meaning out of the עזרה azarah. *azarah*, דקיימא לן בשרפה *de-kaima
lan bi-sreifah*, now we have a, we know, we accept throughout ש"ס
*Shas* that in those cases you burn it, when something happened to
the blood. So מנלן *minalan*? Where do you get that from? That's
not a case that the meat was טמא *tamei* or that the
meat went out. That's something happened to the blood. What's the source
for that? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, we have another
פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. נפקא לה מדרבי שמעון *Nafkah lah mi-de-Rabbi Shimon*, דתניא
*de-tanya*, we learned in a ברייתא *braisa*, רבי שמעון אומר *Rabbi Shimon
omer*, בקודש באש תשרף bakodesh ba'esh tisaref, *ba-kodesh ba-esh tisareif*, in the
holy place you shall burn it with a fire. This is talking
about a חטאת chatas. *chatas*. פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* says וכל חטאת chatas
אשר יובא מדמה אל הקודש פנימה *ve-chol chatas asher yuva mi-damah el
ha-kodesh pnimah*, is that it? Something like that. That's why אהל מועד
*ohel moed*, oh okay very good, וכל חטאת chatat אשר יובא מדמה
אל אהל מועד לכפר בקודש bakodesh לא תאכל באש תשרף *ve-chol chatas
asher yuva mi-damah el ohel moed le-chapeir ba-kodesh lo se-acheil ba-esh tisareif*.
So that's the scenario that you bring the blood inner inside into
the, into the היכל *heichal*, not just in the outer courtyard, not
the עזרה azarah, *azarah*, but into the אהל מועד *ohel moed*, into
the היכל *heichal*, and it's supposed to have been blood on the
outside and that is you burn it. So בקודש באש תשרף bakodesh
ba'esh tisaref *ba-kodesh ba-esh tisareif*, that was like the scenario we were
discussing in the Moshe Aharon exchange. לימד על חטאת chatat ששרפתה בקודש
*Limed al chatas she-sreifasah ba-kodesh*. You see that if a חטאת *chatas*
becomes invalid because something wrong was done with the blood, you burn
it number one. And the other point being made is בקודש באש
תשרף *ba-kodesh ba-esh tisareif*, you burn it on sanctified grounds, you burn
it in the, in the עזרה azarah. *azarah*. אין לי אלא זו
בלבד *Ein li ela zo bilvad*, I only know by a חטאת
*chatas*, שאר פסולי קדשי קדשים psulei kadshei kodshim *shar psulei kodshei kodashim*,
if and when something like this happens to the blood. שאר פסולי
קדשי קדשים *Shar psulei kodshei kodashim* if other invalidities happen to other
A: other sacrifices, B: other invalidities, ואמורי קדשים קלים *ve-imurei kadashim kalim*
or how about something happens to something that was, is, has to
stay in the עזרה azarah, *azarah* but it's קדשים קלים *kadashim kalim*.
It's a שלמים *shelamim* but it's the fats of the שלמים *shelamim*.
So that's the part of the שלמים *shelamim* that has to stay
in the עזרה azarah. *azarah*. מנלן *Minalan*? So how do I know
to expand this beyond חטאת *chatas*? So other types of invalidities for
all things whose zone is the עזרה *azarah*, קדשי קדשים ואמורי קדשי
קדשים *kodshei kodashim ve-imurei kodshei kodashim*. תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*: בקודש באש
תשרף *ba-kodesh ba-esh tisareif*. Somehow you emphasize the end of the פסוק
pasuk, *pasuk*. Any invalidity that happens בקודש *ba-kodesh* in the עזרה *azarah*
for things whose locale is the עזרה *azarah* have to be burned
by a fire and presumably also have to be by a fire
in the עזרה *azarah*, בקודש *ba-kodesh* you burn it in the קודש
kodesh *kodesh*. Right, exactly. Exactly. אשכחן קדשי קדשים *Ashkachan kodshei kodashim*, fine.
That's קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* things whose zone is קודש kodesh *kodesh*.
Okay, קדשים קלים מנלן *kadashim kalim minalan*? How do I know that
the same idea of burning with a fire applies to invalidities on
פסולים psulim *psulim* that occur to קדשים קלים *kadashim kalim* whose zone
is ירושלים *Yerushalayim*? And there by the way as I said you
don't have to burn it in the עזרה *azarah*. How do I
know there that anyway you still have to burn it? אלא *Ela*,
you know what, you're right. We don't have a good פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* for that. The only פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* we had for קדשים
קלים *kadashim kalim* was טמא *tamei*. We don't have a פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* for other invalidities for קדשים קלים *kadashim kalim*. We can cover
most of our things but not for קדשים קלים *kadashim kalim* for
other invalidities. And therefore what we have to admit is, כל פסולא
בקודש בשרפה *kol psula ba-kodesh bi-sreifah*, there's a general rule that anything
that's invalid, any קרבן korban, *korban* that's invalid has to be burned,
לא שנא קדשים קלים ולא שנא קדשי קדשים *lo shena kadashim kalim
ve-lo shena kodshei kodashim*, whether it's קדשים קלים *kadashim kalim* or קדשי
קדשים *kodshei kodashim*. גמרא גמירי לה gemara gemiri la, *G'mora g'miri lah*,
it's a tradition. It's not based on a פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*. Similar
to the discussion the other day about how do we know this
whole הלכה halacha *halacha* of טומאת התהום *tumas ha-tehom*, we tried to
learn it from a פסוק *pasuk* and then we threw up our
hands and we said it's a tradition. So here, the הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha l'moshe m'sinai, *halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai*, right. So what גמרא גמירי
לה gemara gemiri la *g'mora g'miri lah* is different than... Whether it's
קדשי קדשים or קדשי קלים, kodshei kalim, גמרא גמירי לה, gemara gemiri
la it's a tradition, it's not based on a פסוק. Similar to
the discussion the other day about how do we know this whole
הלכה halacha of טומת התהום, tumas hatehom, we try to learn it
from a פסוק and then we threw up our hands and said
it's a tradition. So here, here the גמרא Gemara הלכה למשה מסיני,
halacha l'moshe m'sinai, right? What's true, whether גמרא גמירי לה gemara gemiri
la. is different than הלכה halacha למשה מסיני, there's some discussion in
the אחרונים. acharonim. That's true. Anyway, but the point is that we
got very close. We got certainly in the פסוקים pesukim the idea
of burning פסול קדשים. pasul kodshim. We were even able to expand
it to all קדשי קדשים, we were able to expand it to
טומאה tuma, of קדשי קלים, kodshei kalim, but we couldn't cover every
single case, other פסולים psulim of קדשי קלים, kodshei kalim, so we
had to say that we get this from tradition. Rabbi, and did
these פסולים burn on the מזבח mizbeach or a separate fire? No,
no, no, not on the מזבח, mizbeach, separate fire. Separate fire. Separate
fire going on, yeah, somewhere on the floor, exactly. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. חטאת אהרן, chatas aharon, so why did
we, so this is so funny, the גמרא's Gemara question. Well, if
we already know the הלכה halacha, of when we have to burn,
you know, if we had that tradition, this is why, by the
way, Michael, גמרא גמירי לה gemara gemiri la. seems like it was
a tradition going all the way back. If we already had this
tradition, if we know independently that you burn פסול קדשים, pasul kodshim,
so why did the תורה Torah tell us the whole story of
אהרן? Aharon? I mean, why do we need to know that? Like,
we know the הלכה halacha. already, obviously. The whole assumption is the
only reason the תורה Torah tells a story is that we can
infer הלכה halacha from it. חטאת אהרן, chatas aharon, ומשום מעשה שהיה
כך היה. u'mishum maaseh shehaya kach haya. The story of אהרן, Aharon,
חטאת אהרן, chatas aharon, actually wasn't to teach us הלכה, but just
to tell us the story that actually happened. Okay. All right. Rabbi,
that's an astonishing statement given the people who say that every little
letter, every, no, all right, that's true. Okay, maybe we learn other
things, but it wasn't to teach us that הלכה. ותנא דבי רבה
בר אבוה דאמר אפילו פגול טעון עיבור צורה. vetanna d'vei rabba bar
avuha d'amar afilu pigul taun ibbur tzura. Now, how about the תנא
tanna of רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar Avuha who teaches in another
place that any invalidity that's not, let's say, טומאה, tumah. even something
that's seen as very intrinsic, like פגול, pigul, that actually, that you
thought to eat it at the wrong time, and that's seen as
a very intrinsic, like, status of the קרבן, korban even that you
don't burn immediately, you wait till the next, you wait till the
next morning, you wait till it becomes נותר. nosar, So, so according
to him, מנא ליה? minalei? Where does he get that from? Since
now, presumably, right, it's funny, the תוספות says why couldn't it just
say he didn't have this tradition, he didn't have this גמרא Gemara
גמירי לה. But anyway, the point is that the גמרא Gemara says,
you know, all these פסוקים, pesukim, even if they don't cover a
hundred percent of the cases, really emphasize when something becomes invalid, you
burn it. And presumably, you burn it right away. The nature of
an invalidity is it gets burned. If you say, where does he
get this idea that even if it's invalid, you have to wait
till it becomes invalid, you know, even more, you have to wait
till it's the next morning and it becomes נותר, nosar where does
he get that idea from? So the גמרא Gemara, says, ילף עון
עון מנותר. yalif avon avon minosar. He makes a גזירה שוה. gezeira
shava. It says by פגול pigul עון, avon, and it says by
נותר nosar, עון, avon, sin. So the same way נותר, which is
the classic case in the תורה Torah what you burn when the
meat is left over till the next morning, and that's only burnt
the next morning, any other invalidity you also only burn it the
next morning. So the גמרא says, ולילף עון עון מחטאת אהרן? veleilef
avon avon mechatas aharon? I don't get it. It also says by
אהרן, Aharon, you know, ונשאתם את עון העדה. u'nesasam es avon ha'eidah.
It says עון avon by אהרן's Aharon story, and there presumably they
burnt it right away. So why don't we learn from there that
invalidities you burn right away? So אמר לך, amar lach, all right,
he'll tell you. חטאת אהרן כי האי גוונא נמי עיבור צורה לדורות
בעיא. chatas aharon ki hai gavna nami ibbur tzura l'doros ba'aya. You
know what? If that problem that happened with אהרן Aharon had happened
in a, whatever the problem was, if that had happened in a
normal קרבן, korban. they would have had to wait a day. So
and the reason is, as Michael says, והתם הוראת שעה הייתה. vehasam
horaas shaah haysah. There, it was a special, you know, a special
teaching for that time. Meaning, it was a special case. It was
a special חטאת. It wasn't a normal חטאת. Whatever the reason was
that they burnt it, which we've already suggested something, we're not going
to fully unpack right here, but anyway, that was a special case,
special circumstances, but normally we're not going to learn from that a
general principle. Those two out of, many of the קרבנות korbanos, there
were one time, one in a lifetime קרבנות, korbanos and therefore we're
not going to learn a rule from that about, well, right, according
to רש"י, that's the question about whose שעיר se'ir it was. Okay,
you could look at this a long רש"י. Yes. Yes. So, so
wasn't the reason emotional? Well, the גמרא and the תורה Torah never
tells us. The גמרא speculates on a lot of reasons. אהרן Aharon
says, would this have happened? Right. So right. So the גמרא has
to translate that into halakhic terms. But you're right. I mean, you
know, it's very personal. Yes. In the simple sense of the פסוק,
it's very personal. The גמרא makes it a halakhic debasis. Okay, but
right, but anyway, his point being, so in a way, you could
say what you're saying, you know, but the, it's like, look, whatever
is true about that story, you don't learn any general rules from
it. Okay, that's essentially what he's saying. Although he's saying it still
a little bit more in halakhic terms, that, you know, there's a
special halakhic ruling there, which is not a general rule. Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this. השתא דאמינא כל פסולי דקדש בשריפה,
hashta d'amina kol psulei d'kodesh b'sreifa, לא שנא קדשי קדשים ולא שנא
קדשי קלים, lo shna kodshei kodashim v'lo shna kodshei kalim, גמרא גמירי
לה. Now that we say this idea that you burn all things
that, you know, and we have it as a tradition, whatever the
case is, and generally we'd say you burn it immediately, especially if
it's an intrinsic פסול, psul, against תנא tanna that we just taught.
So anyway, בקודש באש תשרף למה לי? lama li? So back to,
similar to the question why do I need the story of אהרן,
Aharon, why do I need the פסוק that says by the חטאת
that the blood is brought inside, בקודש באש תשרף, you know, who
needs a פסוק? I have a tradition. So the גמרא says, ההוא
מיבעי ליה לשריפה בקודש. hahu miba'ei lei l'sreifa bakodesh. That's not to
tell you that you have to burn it. That's to tell you
where you burn it. That you have to burn it בקודש. That
if it is קדשי קדשים that become פסול, psul something whose zone
is the עזרה, then it has to be burned in the עזרה.
You don't burn it elsewhere. Okay, so now we have the idea
that you burn פסולי קדשי קדשים is a lot in the פסוקים,
psukim, but in the end we're saying it's all tradition. The בקודש
באש תשרף is telling me that if its zone when it was
a good קרבן korban was the עזרה, it has to be burned
in the עזרה. Now, ובשר אשר יגע בכל טמא לא יאכל באש
ישרף v'habasar asher yigah b'chol tamei lo ye'achel ba'esh yisaref למה לי?
lama li? Why do I need the פסוק that tells me burn
meat that becomes טמא? Again, I already know that you burn פסול
קדשים psul kodshim and I already know that if its zone is
the עזרה, you burn it in the עזרה. Why do I need
that פסוק? So the גמרא says, ההיא לגופיה איצטריך. hahi l'gufeih itztareich.
You need it to tell me that very הלכה of טומאה. tumah
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I would have thought, כל פסולי
דקודש, kol psulei d'kodesh, what are the cases that you burn in
קרבנות korbanos, that become invalid? כגון לן דמא k'gon lan dama if
the blood wasn't thrown on the same day, נשפך דמא it was
spilled, ויצא דמא v'yatza dama or the blood was taken out of
the בית המקדש, העזרה, ha'azarah, דנשחטה בלילה d'nishcheta balaylah or if it
was shechted at night. Those things I would have said are the
types of things that you burn בקודש ושרפה. u'sreifa. Why? What makes
those special? דליתנהו בחולין. d'leisnhu b'chulin. That's a type of an invalidity
that only exists with קרבן. korban. So the way it became פסול
psul. was a קרבן korban type of a פסול. psul. So then
I could say, okay, it's basically about it being a קרבן. korban
It's still and therefore you burn it. Because, you know, as a
קרבן korban it became פסול. psul. אבל נטמא, aval nitma, but if
what happened was that it became טמא, you know, that's a very
common פסול. psul, It's not an elitist פסול, psul. it's a common
פסול. psul. דבחולין נמי מיפסל. d'v'chulin nami mipsal. Anything, even non-קרבנות, חולין,
chulin, טומאה tumah affects them. You can't eat it but it affects
its status. So that's a very humdrum common פסול. psul, That type
of a thing, אימא הואיל ואישתרי בהדי עובדין דחול, eima ho'il v'ishtarei
behadi uvdin d'chol, since even the way, you see, people it's very
elitist. Even when you become פסול, psul do you become פסול psul
in your elitist way or in a common way? If you became
פסול psul in a common way, then you become like a commoner.
That really, you know, undermines your status. So then, אימא לא תיבעי
שרפה, eima lo tibei sreifa, you don't deserve burning. Burning is something
we do only for קודש kodesh. if it's a technical little קודש
פסול psul and it retains its status. This type of a thing
maybe completely destroys its status and maybe ותיסגי ליה בקבורה, v'tisgi lei
bikvura, you just bury it, you wouldn't burn it. קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that even by טומאה you burn it. We learn
תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah and then קל וחומר kal v'chomer to קדשים?
Yeah, have to go back and figure out and see which פסוקים
psukim we learn it from and which way the learning goes. Okay,
so let's try to go a little bit further. So that's the
basic principle that you burn and that you burn בקודש if its
zone was קודש. And the distinction between an intrinsic פסול psul and
an extrinsic. Now, although that we haven't focused on too much, we're
going to get to right now. נטמאו בעלים או שמתו nitm'u be'alim
o shemetu רבה בר אבוה צורתן. Rabba bar Avuha tzurasan. If the
owners become טמא or they die, then that's extrinsic to the קרבן
korban and you have to wait till the next morning. Next morning
is יום טוב, Yom Tov, so you wait till the 16th. And
then, whoever it was, said רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka said no, that you can burn immediately on the 14th. ועיבור
צורה v'ibur tzura means if it's תפיסת צורה. tfisas tzura. Exactly. Exactly,
which means you wait till the next morning. It's a for some
reason that's the term to mean wait till the next morning. And
what was the term? ומחלה צורתו, u'm'chaleh tzurato, וגבלו צורתו? v'giblo tzurato?
That's true. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, מחלוקת שנטמאו בעלים אחר
זריקה. machlokes shenitm'u be'alim achar zrika. The debate here whether it's considered
an intrinsic פסול psul. or an extrinsic one is that the זריקה
zrika was done correctly and now the owners died and now there's
nobody to eat it. But when it was brought, everything was fine.
דאיתחזי בשר לאכילה. d'itchazi basar l'achilah. That the meat was initially fit
to be eaten. And therefore the חכמים chachamim say, and then they
die after that, they say it's extrinsic. And רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה
Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka says even that is an intrinsic פסול. psul,
אבל נטמאו בעלים לפני זריקה, aval nitm'u be'alim lifnei zrika, if before
the blood was thrown there were no owners, דלא איתחזי בשר לאכילה,
d'lo itchazi basar l'achilah, that the meat was never fit when the
קרבן korban, was being brought, it was already ownerless at that moment.
דברי הכל תישרף מיד. divrei hakol tisaref miyad. Everybody would say it's
an intrinsic פסול, psul, an ownerless קרבן korban at the... you can't
bring an ownerless קרבן פסח. korban pesach Owners are unable to be
eaten whether they died or became טמא. But if it was brought
when it was not able to be eaten, that is an intrinsic
פסול, psul everybody would agree. מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on this,
says the גמרא, זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the rule. כל
שפסולו בגופו ישרף מיד. kol shepsulo b'gufo yisaref miyad. If it's a
פסול psul. intrinsic, you burn it immediately. בדם ובבעלים תעובר צורתו. bdam
u'v'v'alim te'uvar tzurato. If it's a problem with the blood, it got
spilled or wasn't thrown, or something happened to the owners, then you
wait till the next morning. ויצא לבית השריפה, v'yetzei l'veis hasreifa, you
burn it the next morning, or on יום טוב Yom Tov you
burn it on the 16th. So וקתני, v'katani, okay, בעלים דומיא דדם,
ba'alim dumya dedam, we put דם and בעלים ba'alim in the same
category. So something happened to the blood or something happened to the
owners. מה דם לפני זריקה אף, ma dam lifnei zerikah af, something's
going to happen to the blood to make it invalid, it's going
to happen to the blood before זריקה. zerikah. After the blood has
been thrown, who cares about what happens to the blood? So the
same way the scenario that something happened to the blood was before
זריקה, zerikah, אף בעלים לפני זריקה. af ba'alim lifnei zerikah. Even the
thing that happened to the owners was before. And this ברייתא teaches
that if something happened to the owners and now based on context
we're saying before זריקה, zerikah, nevertheless, you don't burn it immediately. So
you see that there is an opinion that even if it happened
before זריקה, zerikah, it's considered extrinsic and not intrinsic. אלא אי איתמר
הכי איתמר, ela i itmar hachi itmar, so what was said, here's
how Rav Yosef would say it. מחלוקת שנטמאו בעלים לפני זריקה, machlokes
shenitmu ba'alim lifnei zerikah, the debate intrinsic or extrinsic is that the
owners became טמא before the זריקת הדם. So the problem is outside
of the קרבן, korban but when the קרבן is being brought already
the problem is present. And there we can debate is that considered
an intrinsic or an extrinsic פסול. psul דלא חזי בשר לאכילה, d'la
chazi basar l'achilah, that it was never fit. דהוי ליה פסולו בגופו,
dehavei leh psulo begufo, there at least Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka could
say it's intrinsic and the חכמים chachamim could disagree and say it's
extrinsic. אבל נטמאו בעלים לאחר זריקה, aval nitmu ba'alim l'achar zerikah, if
they became טמא after the blood was thrown, דחזי בשר לאכילה, dehazi
basar l'achilah, that when it was brought it was completely fit. In
that case, דברי הכל פסולה מחמת דבר אחר, divrei hakol psulah machamat
davar acher, even Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka would have said that's extrinsic
and you have to wait the next day. ובעי עיבור צורה, u'ba'ei
ibur tzurah, and you wait the next day. ורבי יוחנן אמר, v'Rabbi
Yochanan amar, and since it's debatable, Rabbi Yochanan's going to debate it.
Rabbi Yochanan says, no, we've already proved that they debate before זריקה,
zerikah, that the חכמים chachamim call that an extrinsic פסול psul and
Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka calls that an intrinsic. I'm going to say
they also debate after זריקה. zerikah. אף לאחר זריקה נמי מחלוקת, af
l'achar zerikah nami machlokes, they even debate after זריקה, zerikah, and therefore
even there Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka would say that's considered to be
an intrinsic פסול psul and you burn it. ואזל רבי יוחנן לטעמיה,
v'azal Rabbi Yochanan leta'ameh, he goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רבי
יוחנן, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה ורבי נחמיה אמרו דבר
אחד. Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka v'Rabbi Nechemia amru davar echad. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka that says when something happens to the owners, it's an
intrinsic פסול and you burn it, he says the same as Rabbi
Nechemia. Who's Rabbi Nechemia? We'll see. Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, הא דאמרן,
ha de'amaran, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, that's in our משנה. רבי נחמיה
מאי, Rabbi Nechemia mai, who's Rabbi Nechemia? דתניא, רבי נחמיה אומר, Rabbi
Nechemia omer, we haven't forgotten about Aaron and his sons. בדמי אנינות
נשרפה. bidmei aninut nisrefah. Why in the end did, what was the
answer to Moshe's question? So he says the answer is, is that
Aaron was an אונן, onen, okay, and his remaining sons were אוננים.
onenim. And an אונן, onen, כהן אונן מקריב אונן, kohen onen makriv
onen, but he's not אוכל אונן. ochel onen. Okay, so you're not
allowed to eat the meat as an אונן onen and that's why
he burned it. Okay, so if you can't eat the meat as
an אונן, onen, got a question, right? This is a problem that
occurs to the meat but it's not invalid, it's a problem, you
know, of related to the owners and the ability to eat the
meat. אטו באנינות עבד זריקה באנינות, atu b'aninut avad zerikah b'aninut, yes,
but a כהן גדול kohen gadol is allowed to be מקריב אונן.
makriv onen. So the problem was not the עבודה, avodah, the problem
was and there wasn't a single כהן kohen in the world who
wasn't an אונן onen then. Right. לכן נאמר כאלה, lachen ne'emar ka'eleh,
look what happened, if it happened like this, right, meaning like my
sons died. והא אנינות לאחר זריקה היא. veha aninut l'achar zerikah hi.
Now, אנינות aninut is like לאחר זריקה. lachar zerikah. What does that
mean it's like לאחר זריקה? lachar zerikah? So Rashi says even if
his sons died before he did the זריקה, zerikah, which by the
way he says actually is what happened because according to another explanation
of חז"ל, chazal, he says hey, my other sons weren't מקריב, makriv,
I was מקריב makriv and I'm allowed to be מקריב makriv as
an אונן. onen. But nevertheless regarding the status of the meat, it's
like לאחר זריקה lachar zerikah because as opposed to the קרבן פסח,
קרבן פסח if it doesn't have owners it identifies the identity of
the פסח. The idea of eating a חטאת is not defined by
the כהנים kohanim being אוננים, onenim, right, there's no owners on it.
It does so, whenever the כהנים kohanim became טמא, it's not seen
as a problem in the הקרבה. hakravah. It's only a problem in
the eating of the meat. So here you had a case where
it was a problem of the eating of the meat, not in
the הקרבה, hakravah, and nevertheless they burned it, even though the only
problem was the כהנים. kohanim. דנשרפה לאלתר נשרפה, de'nisrefah l'altar nisrefah, it
was burnt right away. So you see that according to Rabbi Yochanan,
according to at least Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, if there's a problem
in the owners, even if it's a problem after the קרבן has
been brought, like after זריקת הדם by פסח or by a חטאת
where there's no כהנים kohanim to eat it, even after it's been
brought, according to Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka that's seen as an intrinsic
problem in the meat and you would burn it even after even
if a problem comes up after. And according to the חכמים chachamim
even if the problem came before, it's considered extrinsic and you would
not burn it until the next day. Okay, giving away...